RUBÉN PÉREZ-SANZ

UAB and BSE

☑ rubenprzsnz@gmail.comWebpage: Rubén Pérez-Sanz

RESEARCH

Job Market Paper: Firm Heterogeneity and Collective Agreements: a Structural Model of Minimum Wages in Spain

Does widespread coverage of collective agreements introduce inefficiencies in the labour market? How are firms of different sizes affected? Participants in collective agreements set the minimum wage that fits them best, not internalising the effects imposed on non-participants. I analyse minimum wage bargaining and its effects on workers and firms in a model of two-sided heterogeneity with on-the-job search. I estimate the model using Spanish Social Security records for the metal industry in Madrid. By exogenously varying minimum wage levels, I show that large firms gain most from raising minimum wages. This is through two channels. On the one hand, large firms increase their advantage in hiring over small firms. On the other hand, higher minimum wages slow down wage growth. This especially decreases the wage bill for large firms because they hire more experienced workers. Lastly, I find that letting everyone participate in collective bargaining would result in a lower wage floor of $\in 1150$ instead of $\in 1250$. The profits of large firms would be reduced by 4.4% and those of small firms increased by 6.9%.

Working papers

• Union Coordination under the Presence of Externalities and Costs in an Oligopoly Market

EDUCATION

| Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona PhD in Economics Thesis Advisor: Joan Llull | 2018 - Present |
|---|----------------|
| Universitat Autònoma de Barcelona M.Res. in Economics | 2016 - 2018 |
| Universidad Carlos III de Madrid M.Sc. in Economics | 2015 - 2016 |
| CIFF M.Sc. in Statistics | 2008 - 2009 |
| Universidad Autonoma de Madrid Bachelor in Economics | 2002 - 2008 |
| PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE | |
| The Econometrics Journal Replication team | 2021 - Present |
| MOVE Fundation Research Assistant of Joan Llull and Robert Miller | 2020 - Present |
| The Economic Journal Replication team | 2019 - Present |

| Banco Sabadell Research Assistant (Intership) | 2019 |
|---|----------------|
| Santander Bank UK London: Process Design and Change Management Consultant | 2014 - 2015 |
| Banco Santander Process Design and Change Management Consultant | 2011 - 2014 |
| Santander Bank Research Assistant (Internship) | 2010 |
| IBERIA L.A.E. Price Analyst | 2009 |
| Dinners Club Analyst | 2009 |
| HONOURS AND AWARDS | |
| PIF-UAB Predoctoral Fellowship | 2018-2022 |
| Barcelona GSE - UAB IDEA Ph.D. Track Fellowship Agreement | 2017-2018 |
| TEACHING | |
| Econometrics I (undergraduate), UAB Instructor | 2021 Fall |
| Econometrics I (graduate), UAB Teaching assistant of Pau Milan | 2021 Winter |
| Math Brush-up (graduate), UAB Instructor | 2020 Fall |
| Structural Microeconometrics (graduate), UAB Teaching assistant of Joan Llull | 2020 $Winter$ |
| Statistics II (undergraduate), UAB Teaching assistant of Vladimir Zaiats | 2021 Spring |
| Math Brush-up (graduate), UAB Instructor | 2019 Fall |
| SEMINARS AND PRESENTATIONS | |
| SSSI, Moscow, Online | June 2021 |
| Bellaterra Applied Working Group, Online | June~2021 |
| Essex-Barcelona Workshop on Labor Economics, Online | May 2021 |
| Bellaterra Applied Working Group, Online | March 2020 |
| Bellaterra Applied Working Group, Barcelona | May 2019 |
| EVENT ORGANIZATION | |
| Coorganizer: BSE PhD Jamboree | 2019 |
| SUMMER SCHOOLS | |

SKILLS

Programming skills:

Stata, MATLAB, GAUS, LATEX, Eviews, Mathematica, MAPLE, R

Languages:

Spanish (Native) English (Advance) Catalan (Basic), German (Basic).

REFERENCES

Joan Llull

Associate Professor of Economics MOVE, UAB and BSE joan.llull@movebarcelona.eu

Javier Fernandez-Blanco

Associate Professor of Economics UAB, MOVE and BSE javier.fernandez@barcelonagse.eu

Hanna Wang

Assistant Professor MOVE, UAB and BSE hannaw.econ@gmail.com